Inventory of the Cecil Dorrian papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Cecil Dorrian papers
1912-1926
XX223
Hoover Institution Archives
1 manuscript box, 3 album boxes (4.6 linear feet)
Clippings, writings, postcards, and photographs, relating to World War I, postwar reconstruction in Western Europe, the Balkans, the Middle East, and the Russian Revolution and Civil War.
Dorrian, Cecil.
Access
Collection is open for research.
Access to sound recordings, video recordings, or motion picture material requires at least two weeks advance notice. Please contact the Hoover Institution Archives for further information.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
1912-1914 Dorrian wrote for the New York Tribune as a dramatic critic and European representative of the Oscar Morosco Theater Company.
1914 Dorrian began writing for the Newark Evening News as a European Correspondent covering the Western front of the war.
1916 Dorrian covered the Italian front in Rome.
1916 Dorrian was sent to Paris to cover American entry into the war.
1916-1918 Dorrian was a regular contributor to the Newark Evening News and other American and European news publications. She covered the effects of the war in England as well as the international response to America's entry into the war.
1918 Dorrian joined a group of American and French news correspondents, authors, and government officials on a tour of a battlefield in Verdun. One woman was killed, while two people were injured after a grenade exploded in front of Dorrian.
1919-1924 Dorrian provided extensive international coverage of the post-war situation in Europe for the Newark Evening News, including the armistice, Treaty of Versailles, and rise of Mussolini in Italy.
1924 Dorrian was presumably sent to Turkey and Russia to cover the effects of the Bolshevik Revolution and Russian civil war. She continued to provide coverage of post-war reconstruction in general for the Newark Evening News.
1926 Dorrian died of pneumonia, possibly in Russia.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Cecil Dorrian papers contain news clippings, postcards, and photographs relating to World War I, post-WWI reconstruction in Western Europe, the Balkans, the Middle East, the rise of Italian facism, and the Russian Revolution and Civil War. Dorrian was one of the first American female news correspondents to cover the front lines during World War I and traveled extensively throughout Europe from 1914-1924. All articles featured in the collection were written by Dorrian (mostly for the Newark Evening News in New Jersey) and contain both news features as well as opinion pieces on international effects and topics related to the war. Cecil Dorrian was one of the first female news correspondents to cover the front lines of World War I.
Journalists.; Reconstruction (1914-1939)--Europe.; Reconstruction (1914-1939)--Middle East.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; World War, 1914-1918.
- Biographical File, 1917, 1919, 1920, undated (Box-folder 1: 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains original collection acquisition card, travel visas, travel permits granting Dorrian entry into various countries, event pamphlets, and event invitations.
- Correspondence, 1917, undated (Box-folder 1: 2)
  Contains postcards received by Dorrian from various persons and locations, mostly unidentified.
- Writings, 1912-1926, undated
  Contains album collection of articles written by Dorrian and arranged in chronological order. Includes both news features and opinion pieces. Some articles have handwritten notes and commentary by Dorrian written on margins. Series also includes an untitled draft on the political state of post-war Europe, especially France, as well as fragments of clippings from various albums.
  - untitled draft, March 10 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - clippings 1912-1915 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - clippings, 1916-1920 (Box-folder 3: 1-5)
  - clippings, 1921-1924 (Box-folder 4: 1-4)
  - clippings, 1924-1926 (Box-folder 2: 2-4)
  - fragments, undated (Box-folder 4: 5)
- Photographs, circa 1914-1926
  Contains photographs organized into two sub-series, "General" and "Country." Photographs in the country sub-series are organized alphabetically. Notable figures included in the series include: King Alexander I of Yugoslavia, Abdullah I of Jordan, and Cecil Dorrian. Some photographs include commentary or descriptions by Dorrian.
  - General, circa 1914-1926
    - unidentified, circa 1914-1926 (Box-folder 1: 4)
      Contains photographic prints of various people, locations, and groups unidentified. Some photos contain observations or descriptions by Dorrian, either too general to determine exact location or illegible.
    - Cecil Dorrian, circa 1914-1926 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Country, circa 1914-1926
    - Albania, circa 1914-1926 (Box-folder 1: 6)
    - Austria, circa 1914-1926 (Box-folder 1: 6)
    - Egypt, circa 1914-1926 (Box-folder 1: 7)
    - France, circa 1914-1926 (Box-folder 1: 7)
    - Greece, 1920, circa 1914-1926 (Box-folder 1: 8)
    - Italy, circa 1914-1926 (Box-folder 1: 8)
    - Israel, circa 1914-1926 (Box-folder 1: 8)
    - Romania, circa 1914-1926 (Box-folder 1: 9)
    - Russia, circa 1914-1926 (Box-folder 1: 10)
    - Serbia, circa 1914-1926 (Box-folder 1: 11)
    - Turkey, 1920, circa 1914-1926 (Box-folder 1: 12)
- Printed Matter, circa 1914-1926
  Contains postcards of various locations and persons significant to the First World War, some with commentary by Dorrian. Organized alphabetically by country.
  - Postcards, circa 1914-1926
    - General, circa 1914-1926 (Box-folder 1: 13)
    - France, circa 1914-1926 (Box-folder 1: 14)
    - Germany, circa 1914-1926 (Box-folder 1: 14)
    - Hungary, circa 1914-1926 (Box-folder 1: 14)
    - Italy, circa 1914-1926 (Box-folder 1: 15)
    - Poland, circa 1914-1926 (Box-folder 1: 15)
    - Serbia, circa 1914-1926 (Box-folder 1: 16-17)
    - Switzerland, circa 1914-1926 (Box-folder 1: 18)
    - Turkey, 1920 April 15, circa 1914-1926 (Box-folder 1: 19)